- [Narrator] Take a look at
this satellite image from China.
At first glance, it shows nothing
but an empty, arid, desert landscape,
but right in the middle
there's something unusual,
some kind of structure.
As we zoom in, we can see
it looks just like an aircraft carrier,
the kind used by
militaries around the world
as floating air bases
complete with runways,
fighter jets and weapons.
But this one isn't in the ocean,
but in the middle of the desert.
Let's zoom out for some context.
The satellite image was taken
over to Taklamakan Desert
in Northwestern China.
Normally, aircraft carriers operate
in the harsh conditions of the open sea,
but this region, while far
more dry, is no less extreme.
From a global perspective,
the Taklamakan Desert
is a fascinating place.
Unlike the surrounding
deserts made of rock,
this one is made of sand.
In fact, it is the second
largest sand desert in the world.
Vast, uninhabited and
seemingly untouched by humans,
it stretches out like a
giant eye made of sand,
a landscape so alien,
it almost looks like it
belongs to another planet.
So why, of all places,
would the Chinese military
built these structures here?
In recent years, China has
made increasing headlines
for its expanding
aircraft carrier project.
- China's first domestically-built
aircraft carrier
has entered service.
- China has clearly invested
in this defense industrial infrastructure
to produce these ships.
- [Narrator] Just 15 years ago,
China didn't have a
single aircraft carrier.
Today it has three.
But if we take a closer look at the shape
in the satellite image,
something doesn't add up.
The design doesn't match
that of China's own carriers.
Instead, the structure
strongly resembles the design
of the American ones.
For comparison, here is
the distinctive shape
of the Gerald R. Ford-class carrier,
the latest in the US Navy's fleet.
Moving slightly away from this location,
we can see a path cutting
through the desert.
This appears to be train tracks
and on the other side of the tracks,
yet another structure comes into view.
This one doesn't look
like an aircraft carrier,
but it has a striking resemblance
to an Arleigh Burke-class destroyer,
one of the most widely used
warships in the US Navy.
The similarity is unmistakable,
not just because of its general shape,
but because of the precise
outlines of key features,
like the ship's bridge, its funnels,
and even the vertical launch system
used for firing missiles.
But it also doesn't look
quite like the real ship.
It looks more like a flat mock-up,
a replica built to mimic the real thing.
Examining historical satellite images
confirms this suspicion.
We can see that in 2020,
the site first appeared
as a grid of cubes with
several tall structures,
possibly masts or antennas
arranged in the shape
of the American warship.
Only later, the full outline of the ship
was marked more clearly.
The aircraft carrier shape
also appears to be just a mock-up.
Here, older satellite images
show that this spot originally
had a different layout,
featuring three distinct shapes,
a small and a medium sized
outline of an aircraft carrier
and the largest version drawn
with those tall metal poles.
And when we look again at the train tracks
running through the middle,
we can see just how strange they are.
Instead of running straight,
the track curves and twists
before making a sharp right turn.
This is odd because the surrounding desert
is completely flat land,
so there are absolutely
no natural obstacles
that would require these turns.
Why wasn't the track
built in a straight line?
And it gets even stranger
when we follow where these tracks lead.
Heading north, they come to
a stop at a base facility
with a large hangar,
a few supporting buildings
and a lot of trucks nearby.
And when following the tracks
the other way heading south,
they simply vanish into the
desert as the tracks just end,
with no sign of ongoing
construction and no clear purpose.
To get close to understanding why China
is doing all of this,
it's helpful to take a look
at where the real counterparts
of these mock-up ships are located
because it turns out US aircraft carriers
often aren't as far away from this desert
as one might think.
- [Reporter 1] The United States
has deployed an aircraft
carrier to the South China Sea.
- [Reporter 2] A Chinese warship
almost running into an
American destroyer on Saturday.
- [Narrator] Tensions in
the waters around China
have been escalating for years,
leading to frequent confrontation
between the US and China.
At the center of these disputes
are two major conflicts,
the South China Sea and Taiwan.
In the South China Sea,
multiple nations lay claim
to various overlapping territories
and China asserts its claim
over almost the entire sea,
treating the ocean as its
own national territory
rather than international waters.
To reinforce this claim,
China has artificially
expanded low-lying islands
and underwater reefs,
covering them with sand
and transforming them
into military outposts.
The US in response
regularly sends warships
through these waters
and conducts military exercises.
The purpose of these
so-called freedom of navigation operations
is to challenge China's
territorial claims on the sea.
But this is just one
reason why US carriers
are present near China.
The second major conflict
is the increasingly tense situation
between China and Taiwan.
- [Reporter 3] Tensions
over Taiwan look no closer
to a peaceful resolution.
- [Reporter 4] Beijing claims Taiwan
as part of its territory.
- [Narrator] While Taiwan defacto operates
as a fully independent nation
with its own government,
mainland China views it
as a renegade province,
one that if necessary,
could be brought under control by force.
The threat of a Chinese
invasion of Taiwan is very real
and it is something the US opposes,
which is why the US Navy
maintains a strong presence
in the Taiwan Strait,
two serious conflicts
that have the potential
to become much worse
and China is preparing for
them by using their desert
as a practice ground for
a potential future war.
The structures are practice targets
built to test whether Chinese missiles
can accurately strike US warships.
Some experts believe
that the many vertical
metal poles could be sensors
used to study the impact
of missile strikes
on these targets.
Another theory is that
they are radar reflectors
placed to better simulate
the complex metal structure
of an actual vessel
so that radar guided
attacks can be tested.
And satellite images from a
different test site confirms
China is hitting their targets.
But striking a stationary
target is one thing.
A real warship, of course,
wouldn't just sit still,
and that is where the train
tracks come into play.
When following the exact
path of the tracks,
we find yet another
aircraft carrier mock-up,
this one perhaps the most
elaborate of them all,
a three dimensional model complete
with numerous poles sticking
up from its structure.
A photograph taken at a
Chinese arms convention appears
to show a scale model of this very system.
And according to these photos,
the mock-up was developed
by the Chinese arms manufacturer, CASIC.
Experts believe that the curves
in the track are designed
so China can simulate
a United States carrier
taking evasive maneuvers
to avoid being hit.
They can simulate a carrier
taking two sharp turns
to avoid being tracked by a missile
or speeding off to get out
of the possible impact zone.
And once again, satellite imagery suggests
that these tests have been successful.
Now, China isn't the only
country building mock-ups
of American warships.
In 2014, Iran constructed a replica
of a US aircraft carrier,
this one even seaworthy.
They used it for missile tests
and then repeatedly
bombed it until it sank,
an exercise that gained
international media attention.
Even though propaganda may
have played a larger role
than actual practice
in this specific case,
training with mock-up targets
is a common military practice,
and the US is doing this all the time,
building elaborate fake
towns in their own deserts
and even training with their own mock-ups.
For instance, a replica of
China's Chengdu J-20 fighter jet
was spotted at a US Air
Force base in Georgia,
and it's well documented
that the US military
has operated fully
functional Russians Su-27
and the MiG-29 fighter
jets on American soil
for training purposes.
But what makes these mock-ups
particularly concerning for the US
is that China isn't
testing ordinary weapons.
China is using these tests
to demonstrate a system
that could fundamentally
change military strategy
in both conflicts mentioned before.
US intelligence assumes
that China possesses a specialized variant
of its Dongfeng 21D missile
that is specifically designed to target
and destroy moving warships
like aircraft carriers.
(missile roaring)
This Chinese missile follows
a ballistic trajectory,
launching high into the atmosphere
before plummeting back
down at extreme speeds.
Then, during the descent phase,
a maneuverable reentry vehicle
separates from the missile.
And unlike a traditional
ballistic war head,
this one can adjust its course in midair,
allowing it to strike
smaller, more precise targets
and even track and hit moving ships.
To support this system,
China has also expanded
its satellite network,
improving its ability to track
moving targets in real time.
Experts believe that defending
against this kind of weapon
is extremely difficult.
Unlike short range missiles or torpedoes,
which require a submarine
to get dangerously close
to an aircraft carrier,
this system enables
China to attack US ships
from medium range in mainland China.
This means conventional US
surface-to-air defense systems
may not be able to react quickly enough
to intercept the missile
during the mid-flight phase.
And in the final phase,
interception becomes even more difficult
due to the maneuverable reentry vehicle,
which follows an unpredictable flight path
and could potentially
execute evasive maneuvers.
Conducting these tests in
the middle of the desert
fully visible to satellites
could be seen as an intentional message,
as it is to the benefit of China
if these capabilities are known.
That is, because the mere
existence of this technology
is already shifting the balance of power.
If the US cannot bring their carriers
within striking distance of missile,
they are forced to operate
them farther away from China,
which would put the conflict
zones outside the range
of the aircraft stationed on the carrier,
practically negating the
use of such carriers.
And so, without ever
needing to use the weapon,
its presence is
strengthening China's ability
to project power in these conflict zones.
Taiwan is also preparing
for this possibility
and the country
has recently announced a
large scale military drill,
simulating a Chinese
invasion of the island,
with over 22,000 reservists taking part.
So far, this story hasn't been picked up
by many major US news outlets,
but it's an important
development to follow.
And to help myself keep
track of stories like this,
I love using this video's
sponsor, Ground News.
The idea behind Ground News is simple,
but it completely changed
how I stay on top of global events.
Ground News doesn't
write its own articles.
Instead, it collects coverage
from a wide range of sources
and organizes them by story.
At the top of each story,
you get a quick summary
of what's going on.
You can instantly see how coverage differs
between left and right-leaning sources.
In this case, Ground News shows
that the Taiwan story has
been covered by 23 sources,
36% left, 43% center, and 21% right.
Bloomberg, a left-leaning outlet,
frames the drills as President Lai
choosing to confront China,
implying Taiwan is provoking tension.
On the right,
"The Epoch Times" emphasizes
the threat from the CCP,
portraying Taiwan's actions as defensive.
With Ground News, you can instantly spot
these kinds of framing differences
and get a more complete perspective
on what's really happening.
In fact, Ground News has
a whole page dedicated
to tracking stories with
the biggest coverage gap,
and it lets you track your
own reading habits over time
so you can which outlets and
topics you gravitate towards,
a great way to see where your
own blind spots might be.
So head to ground.news/neo
or click the button on screen right now
to try Ground News today.
And if you use that exact link,
you'll even get 40%
off their Vantage plan,
which is their most elaborate plan,
and you'll be supporting my
channel at the same time.
So thanks for checking out Ground News
and thank you so much for watching.